<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "https://www.fgdc.gov/schemas/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd"[]>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Program</origin>
        <pubdate>20200816</pubdate>
        <title>USGS National Hydrography Dataset Best Resolution (NHD) for Hydrologic Unit (HU) 8 - 06010202 (published 20200816)</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) is a feature-based database that interconnects and uniquely identifies the stream
				segments or reaches that make up the nation's surface water drainage system. NHD data was originally developed at 1:100,000-scale and
				exists at that scale for the whole country. This high-resolution NHD, generally developed at 1:24,000/1:12,000 scale, adds detail to
				the original 1:100,000-scale NHD. (Data for Alaska, Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands was developed at high-resolution, not 1:100,000
				scale.) Local resolution NHD is being developed where partners and data exist. The NHD contains reach codes for networked features,
				flow direction, names, and centerline representations for areal water bodies. Reaches are also defined on waterbodies and the
				approximate shorelines of the Great Lakes, the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans and the Gulf of Mexico. The NHD also incorporates the
				National Spatial Data Infrastructure framework criteria established by the Federal Geographic Data Committee.</abstract>
      <purpose>The NHD is a national framework for assigning reach addresses to water-related entities, such as industrial discharges, drinking
				water supplies, fish habitat areas, wild and scenic rivers. Reach addresses establish the locations of these entities relative to one
				another within the NHD surface water drainage network, much like addresses on streets. Once linked to the NHD by their reach
				addresses, the upstream/downstream relationships of these water-related entities--and any associated information about them--can be
				analyzed using software tools ranging from spreadsheets to geographic information systems (GIS). GIS can also be used to combine
				NHD-based network analysis with other data layers, such as soils, land use and population, to help understand and display their
				respective effects upon one another. Furthermore, because the NHD provides a nationally consistent framework for addressing and
				analysis, water-related information linked to reach addresses by one organization (national, state, local) can be shared with other
				organizations and easily integrated into many different types of applications to the benefit of all.</purpose>
      <supplinf>This data comprises hydrological data, including flow lines, water bodies and water features.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1988</begdate>
          <enddate>2012</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Irregular</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-83.820228577</westbc>
        <eastbc>-83.143413804</eastbc>
        <northbc>35.5800094590001</northbc>
        <southbc>34.9033714610001</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Geospatial Platform</themekt>
        <themekey>ngda</themekey>
        <themekey>Hydrography</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>rivers</themekey>
        <themekey>lakes</themekey>
        <themekey>dams</themekey>
        <themekey>HUC</themekey>
        <themekey>Subwatershed</themekey>
        <themekey>Watershed Boundary Dataset</themekey>
        <themekey>Watershed Boundaries</themekey>
        <themekey>boundaries</themekey>
        <themekey>Hydrologic Unit Code</themekey>
        <themekey>Basin</themekey>
        <themekey>WBD</themekey>
        <themekey>Region</themekey>
        <themekey>Hydrologic Units</themekey>
        <themekey>Topographic</themekey>
        <themekey>Boundary</themekey>
        <themekey>HU10</themekey>
        <themekey>HU12</themekey>
        <themekey>HU14</themekey>
        <themekey>HU16</themekey>
        <themekey>HU2</themekey>
        <themekey>HU4</themekey>
        <themekey>HU6</themekey>
        <themekey>HU8</themekey>
        <themekey>Area of Complex Channels</themekey>
        <themekey>Area to be submerged</themekey>
        <themekey>artificial path</themekey>
        <themekey>Bay/Inlet</themekey>
        <themekey>Bridge</themekey>
        <themekey>Canal/Ditch</themekey>
        <themekey>Coastline</themekey>
        <themekey>Connector</themekey>
        <themekey>Dam/Weir</themekey>
        <themekey>Estuary</themekey>
        <themekey>Flow direction network</themekey>
        <themekey>Flume</themekey>
        <themekey>ForeShore</themekey>
        <themekey>Gaging Station</themekey>
        <themekey>Gate</themekey>
        <themekey>Hazard Zone</themekey>
        <themekey>Ice mass</themekey>
        <themekey>Inundation Area</themekey>
        <themekey>Levee</themekey>
        <themekey>Lock Chamber</themekey>
        <themekey>Marsh</themekey>
        <themekey>Nonearthen Shore</themekey>
        <themekey>Orthoimage</themekey>
        <themekey>Playa</themekey>
        <themekey>Pond</themekey>
        <themekey>Rapids</themekey>
        <themekey>Rapids</themekey>
        <themekey>Reach code</themekey>
        <themekey>Reach</themekey>
        <themekey>Reef</themekey>
        <themekey>Reservoir</themekey>
        <themekey>Rock</themekey>
        <themekey>Sea/Ocean</themekey>
        <themekey>Sink/Rise</themekey>
        <themekey>Sounding Datum Line</themekey>
        <themekey>Special Use Zone Limit</themekey>
        <themekey>Special Use Zone</themekey>
        <themekey>Spillway</themekey>
        <themekey>Stream/River</themekey>
        <themekey>stream</themekey>
        <themekey>Submerged Stream</themekey>
        <themekey>surface water systems</themekey>
        <themekey>Swamp</themekey>
        <themekey>Tunnel</themekey>
        <themekey>Underground Conduit</themekey>
        <themekey>Wall</themekey>
        <themekey>Wash</themekey>
        <themekey>Water Intake Outflow</themekey>
        <themekey>Waterfall</themekey>
        <themekey>Well</themekey>
        <themekey>Administrative watershed units</themekey>
        <themekey>Sub-region</themekey>
        <themekey>Watershed</themekey>
        <themekey>Sub-basin</themekey>
        <themekey>Watershed Boundary Dataset</themekey>
        <themekey>WBD</themekey>
        <themekey>Hydrography</themekey>
        <themekey>Hydrographic</themekey>
        <themekey>Line</themekey>
        <themekey>Point</themekey>
        <themekey>PointEvent</themekey>
        <themekey>Subbasin</themekey>
        <themekey>Subregion</themekey>
        <themekey>Boundaries</themekey>
        <themekey>Administrative watershed units</themekey>
        <themekey>Basin</themekey>
        <themekey>Drainage areas for surface water</themekey>
        <themekey>drainage systems and characteristics</themekey>
        <themekey>National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) Best Resolution</themekey>
        <themekey>HU-8 Subbasin</themekey>
        <themekey>FileGDB 10.1</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>US</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
      </place>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System</placekt>
        <placekey>US</placekey>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
        <placekey>NC</placekey>
        <placekey>North Carolina</placekey>
        <placekey>GA</placekey>
        <placekey>Georgia</placekey>
        <placekey>TN</placekey>
        <placekey>Tennessee</placekey>
        <placekey>Blount County</placekey>
        <placekey>Cherokee County</placekey>
        <placekey>Clay County</placekey>
        <placekey>Graham County</placekey>
        <placekey>Jackson County</placekey>
        <placekey>Macon County</placekey>
        <placekey>Rabun County</placekey>
        <placekey>Sevier County</placekey>
        <placekey>Swain County</placekey>
        <placekey>HU8_06010202</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None. However, users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this data set was collected and that some parts
			of this data may no longer represent actual surface conditions. Users should not use this data for critical applications without a full
			awareness of its limitations. Acknowledgment of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated for products derived from these
			data.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>https://prd-tnm.s3.amazonaws.com/StagedProducts/Hydrography/NHD/HU8/HighResolution/GDB/NHD_H_06010202_HU8_GDB.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Thumbnail JPG image</browsed>
      <browset>JPEG</browset>
    </browse>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Statements of attribute accuracy are based on accuracy statements made for U.S. Geological Survey Digital Line Graph (DLG) data,
				which is estimated to be 98.5 percent. One or more of the following methods were used to test attribute accuracy: manual comparison of
				the source with hardcopy plots; symbolized display of the DLG on an interactive computer graphic system; selected attributes that
				could not be visually verified on plots or on screen were interactively queried and verified on screen. In addition, software
				validated feature types and characteristics against a master set of types and characteristics, checked that combinations of types and
				characteristics were valid, and that types and characteristics were valid for the delineation of the feature. Feature types,
				characteristics, and other attributes conform to the Standards for National Hydrography Dataset (USGS, 1999) as of the date they were
				loaded into the database. All names were validated against a current extract from the Geographic Names Information System (GNIS). The
				entry and identifier for the names match those in the GNIS. The association of each name to reaches has been interactively checked,
				however, operator error could in some cases apply a name to a wrong reach.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Points, nodes, lines, and areas conform to topological rules. Lines intersect only at nodes, and all nodes anchor the ends of lines.
			Lines do not overshoot or undershoot other lines where they are supposed to meet. There are no duplicate lines. Lines bound areas and
			lines identify the areas to the left and right of the lines. Gaps and overlaps among areas do not exist. All areas close.</logic>
    <complete>The completeness of the data reflects the content of the sources, which most often are the published USGS topographic quadrangle
			and/or the USDA Forest Service Primary Base Series (PBS) map. The USGS topographic quadrangle is usually supplemented by Digital
			Orthophoto Quadrangles (DOQs). Features found on the ground may have been eliminated or generalized on the source map because of scale and
			legibility constraints. In general, streams longer than one mile (approximately 1.6 kilometers) were collected. Most streams that flow
			from a lake were collected regardless of their length. Only definite channels were collected so not all swamp/marsh features have
			stream/rivers delineated through them. Lake/ponds having an area greater than 6 acres were collected. Note, however, that these general
			rules were applied unevenly among maps during compilation. Reach codes are defined on all features of type stream/river, canal/ditch,
			artificial path, coastline, and connector. Waterbody reach codes are defined on all lake/pond and most reservoir features. Names were
			applied from the GNIS database. Detailed capture conditions are provided for every feature type in the Standards for National Hydrography
			Dataset available online through http://mapping.usgs.gov/standards/.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Statements of horizontal positional accuracy are based on accuracy statements made for U.S. Geological Survey topographic
					quadrangle maps. These maps were compiled to meet National Map Accuracy Standards. For horizontal accuracy, this standard is met
					if at least 90 percent of points tested are within 0.02 inch (at map scale) of the true position. Additional offsets to positions
					may have been introduced where feature density is high to improve the legibility of map symbols. In addition, the digitizing of
					maps is estimated to contain a horizontal positional error of less than or equal to 0.003 inch standard error (at map scale) in
					the two component directions relative to the source maps. Visual comparison between the map graphic (including digital scans of
					the graphic) and plots or digital displays of points, lines, and areas, is used as control to assess the positional accuracy of
					digital data. Digital map elements along the adjoining edges of data sets are aligned if they are within a 0.02 inch tolerance (at
					map scale). Features with like dimensionality (for example, features that all are delineated with lines), with or without like
					characteristics, that are within the tolerance are aligned by moving the features equally to a common point. Features outside the
					tolerance are not moved; instead, a feature of type connector is added to join the features.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Statements of vertical positional accuracy for elevation of water surfaces are based on accuracy statements made for U.S.
					Geological Survey topographic quadrangle maps. These maps were compiled to meet National Map Accuracy Standards. For vertical
					accuracy, this standard is met if at least 90 percent of well-defined points tested are within one-half contour interval of the
					correct value. Elevations of water surface printed on the published map meet this standard; the contour intervals of the maps
					vary. These elevations were transcribed into the digital data; the accuracy of this transcription was checked by visual comparison
					between the data and the map.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, USDA Forest Service, and other
							Federal, State and local partners. National Hydrography Dataset is a component of a comprehensive base geospatial data
							model.</origin>
            <pubdate>20200816</pubdate>
            <title>Hydrography</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) is a feature-based database that interconnects and uniquely identifies the
							stream segments or reaches that make up the nation's surface water drainage system. The high-resolution NHD was originally
							created using 1:24,000-scale data. State and Local Stewards are improving the data by incorporating local updates based on
							more current and more accurate source data. Water features in the real world are relatively dynamic and the differences at
							the time of data collection mean that water features may not register exactly to other layers. The hydrographic feature
							names contained in and displayed by the NHD are extracted and validated from the Geographic Names Information System
							(GNIS). Spatial objects may be filtered or generalized to achieve a 1:24,000-scale representation.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nhd.usgs.gov/</onlink>
            <onlink>http://nhd.usgs.gov/gnis.html</onlink>
            <onlink>http://nhdgeo.usgs.gov/metadata/nhd_high.htm</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20100820</begdate>
              <enddate>20100820</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Hydrography</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Hydrography features and feature names</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Global Land Ice Measurements from Space initiative (GLIMS)</origin>
            <pubdate>20200816</pubdate>
            <title>Gaging Stations</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>This dataset, termed "GAGES II", an acronym for Geospatial Attributes of Gages for Evaluating Streamflow, version
							II, provides geospatial data and classifications for 9,322 stream gages maintained by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS).
							It is an update to the original GAGES in 2010. The GAGES II dataset consists of gages which have had either 20+ complete
							years (not necessarily continuous) of discharge record since 1950, or are currently active, as of water year 2009, and
							whose watersheds lie within the United States, including Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico. Only active stations, as
							identified by the GAGES II dataset, are symbolized.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/lookup/getspatial?gagesII_Sept2011</onlink>
            <onlink>http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/XML/gagesII_Sept2011.xml</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>digital data</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate />
              <enddate />
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Hydrography - Gaging Stations</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Hydrography features and gaging stations</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</origin>
            <pubdate>20200816</pubdate>
            <title>Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD)</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <othercit>The Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD) defines the areal extent of surface water drainage to a point, accounting for
							all land and surface areas. Watershed Boundaries are determined solely upon science-based hydrologic principles, not
							favoring any administrative boundaries or special projects, nor particular program or agency. The intent of defining
							Hydrologic Units (HU) for the Watershed Boundary Dataset is to establish a base-line drainage boundary framework,
							accounting for all land and surface areas. Hydrologic units are given a Hydrologic Unit Code (HUC). For example, a
							hydrologic region has a 2-digit HUC. A HUC describes where the unit is in the country and the level of the
							unit.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://nhd.usgs.gov/wbd.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>24000</srcscale>
        <typesrc>None</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>19720101</begdate>
              <enddate>20120101</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Watershed Boundary Dataset</srccitea>
        <srccontr>U.S. Geological Survey</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>New reaches were assigned reach code values that are sequentially ordered to 2-D and then 1-D reaches. New high-res reach
					codes are larger than any existing med-res reach code in the associated Catalog Unit. Additional Geographic Names that exist in
					the Geographic Names Information System (GNIS) were added to reaches in the high-res dataset. Names for the high-res drainage
					network were interactively transferred from the vector GNIS coverage. Additional GNIS names for point and water body features were
					also added.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20200816</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>0.00001</latres>
        <longres>0.00001</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.2572221</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>All feature types, characteristics, and values are in U.S. Geological Survey, 1999, Standards for National Hydrography Dataset:
				Reston, Virginia, U.S. Geological Survey. The document is available online through http://nationalmap.gov/standards/nhdstds.html.
				Information about tables and fields in the data are available from the user documentation for the National Hydrography Dataset
				available online through http://nhd.usgs.gov/documentation.html.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>http://nhd.usgs.gov/userguide.html</eadetcit>
      <eadetcit>http://nhd.usgs.gov/documentation.html</eadetcit>
      <eadetcit>http://nationalmap.gov/standards/nhdstds.html</eadetcit>
      <eadetcit>https://prd-wret.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/assets/palladium/production/atoms/files/NHD%20v2.3%20Model%20Poster%2006012020.pdf</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>MO</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Box 25046 Denver Federal Center</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>http://www.usgs.gov/ask/</cntemail>
        <hours>Monday through Friday 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM</hours>
        <cntinst>Metadata information can also be obtained through online services using The National Map Viewer, at
					http://nationalmap.usgs.gov or EarthExplorer, at http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov or Ask USGS at http://www.usgs.gov/ask.</cntinst>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
    <distliab>No liability for content or accuracy is presumed by USGS for data.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>FileGDB</formname>
          <formvern>10.1</formvern>
          <formcont>Spatial objects with unique identifiers and coordinate data.</formcont>
          <filedec>No compression applied</filedec>
          <transize>15433126</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://prd-tnm.s3.amazonaws.com/StagedProducts/Hydrography/NHD/HU8/HighResolution/GDB/NHD_H_06010202_HU8_GDB.zip</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20200816</metd>
    <metrd>20130216</metrd>
    <metfrd>20140216</metfrd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Geospatial Technical Operations Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>MO</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Box 25046 Denver Federal Center</address>
          <city>Lakewood</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-ASK-USGS (1-888-275-8747)</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>http://www.usgs.gov/ask/</cntemail>
        <hours>Monday through Friday 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM</hours>
        <cntinst>Metadata information can also be obtained through online services using The National Map Viewer, at
					http://nationalmap.usgs.gov or EarthExplorer, at http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov or Ask USGS at http://www.usgs.gov/ask.</cntinst>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>